thank you
okay calm down
as someone who obviously served prison
um time what what do you want people to
know about that experience especially as
we're talking about people who are
facing prison time now
wow where do you even begin the the U.S
uh prison system at every level at the
federal level the state level and local
levels is utterly and completely broken
I did a piece just a week ago for
Consortium news in which I went over
um just as a a random sampling
um uh 15 or 20 prison guards that have
been arrested in the last two years
about a third of them have been arrested
for raping prisoners both female and
male the other two-thirds have been
arrested for smuggling into prisons cell
phones and Drugs in many cases hard
drugs that ended up killing prisoners
that they were selling the drugs to uh
the system is completely broken
you know there's a book that was written
by Dr Peter moskos of
um John Jay College school of uh
criminal justice it's called in defense
of flogging which is kind of a
tongue-in-cheek title but he makes a
conclusion that I think is very very
important in this book he says that at
the federal level the Federal Bureau of
Prisons really is nothing more than an
employment agency for otherwise
unemployable
undereducated rural white men
these are guys who couldn't make it in
the military
these are guys who were flunkies from
the local police academy and just
couldn't make a career out of law
enforcement and in the United States our
prisons are almost entirely in rural
areas and they serve as the only sources
of um of jobs and thus of income for a
lot of rural white men
well
do you know what the qualifications are
for a prison guard in America and I mean
this quite literally you need a GED
and no felony convictions
and that's it
it's no wonder that they turn to
corruption and drugs and smuggling and
rape and end up committing suicide and
and beating people and abusing people
and standing by while they commit
suicide and
again the the entire
the entire system is broken it needs to
be scrapped and rebuilt all right let me
get still standing on my soapbox here
until Ronald Reagan was elected
president you could go to prison in the
United States and uh with good behavior
you could get out on federal parole
there is no federal parole anymore
thanks to the so-called prison reform
Act of 1986. now you get five years or
you get 10 years you're doing five years
or ten years
uh time also used to be where you could
go to prison and learn a skill you could
learn to be a plumber or an electrician
or you could fix engines or you know
whatever learn how to do whatever
Landscaping well they don't do any of
that anymore
so let's say as an example you're doing
five years or ten years on a drug charge
they don't teach you how to read and
write they don't uh they don't give you
classes so you can pass the time they
don't give you a skill that you can then
adopt as a vocation when you get out
they send you straight back to the
neighborhood that you came from
and you are not only no better off than
you were when you went to prison
but now you have PTSD and you're pissed
off right and so what are you gonna do
you're gonna do the only thing you know
how to do and that is to sell drugs
again when I was released
um I was released first to a halfway
house
called Hope Village in Washington it is
now defunct for good reason we used to
call it abandon all hope Village there
were 220 men in this uh in this facility
there was one count it there was one job
that was posted on the bulletin board
and it was to be a dishwasher at
Fuddruckers and there were 220 guys
beating the hell out of each other to
get that one dishwasher job because once
you had the job you could then transfer
to your home
and then have permission to leave home
to go to the dishwasher job
broken with a capital B
and then of course our uh it's also
broken in terms of who is uh convicted
in the first place because you had the
honor of being sent to prison the only
person sent to prison over the CIA
torture program was not the person who
not a person who tortured people but it
was someone who exposed it
yeah my first couple days in prison were
were eye-opening uh as I would walk past
the guards they would whisper traitor
which I'm sure they had all been sort of
prompted to do sure and you know
how did they want me to react did they
want me to like take a swing at them
right so that they could send me to
solitary I the first couple times I just
kind of chuckled like whatever dope
um and then after that I just ignored
them until they stopped doing it
um but yeah you're right you know there
there were a lot of things that I had to
learn very quickly in prison number one
was that it's like walking into 1950s
America in that literally everything is
divided along racial lines everything
um there are blacks whites and Hispanics
and if you don't fit neatly into one of
those categories then you better squeeze
yourself into one of those categories
where is it where do the Greek Americans
go yeah I sat with the Italians which
were an extension of the the whites
which really were the Aryans
so um what you have to do on your very
first day is you have to show your
paperwork which
colloquially means you have to prove
that you're not a pedophile
so I showed my paperwork I'm not in on a
child sex charge so I was allowed to sit
with the Aryans and the Aryan section in
the cafeteria was divided between honest
to God Nazis and then what were called
good guys that is white guys
um who are not pedophiles
next to them were the Italians the
Italians of course all sat together and
my second year in prison I was invited
to sit with the Italians so I moved over
there and I mean Italians named Gambino
banano Lucchesi Genovese you get the
idea
and then there was a table of um Native
Americans
and then on the white side all the other
tables were pedophiles and rats the rats
had to sit with pedophiles the other
half of the cafeteria was all black
and whites couldn't sit over there and
blacks couldn't sit on the white side
well in the TV room the day room I was
one of the people who chose to ignore uh
those those racial uh divisions they
just never made sense to me
and so
um I was lucky not realizing it at the
time I was lucky in the very beginning
of my my prison sentence that I was in a
cell with
both
um uh black guys and Mexican guys
and when I showed that I wasn't a rat
and I wasn't a pedophile and I was
educated so I'm happy to help you uh
write your appeal which you're gonna
lose anyway but I'm happy to help you
write it
then I got the thumbs up from all the
different racial groups and everything
was cool wow
wow that's insane it was it was hard wow
and you were there two years three years
yeah 23 months so just under just barely
under two years